Guide to the John F. Embree papers, 1932-2001.
Embree, John F. papers, 1932-2001.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
John F. Embree papers, 1932-2001.
6475
John F. (John Fee) Embree, 1908-1950.
4 cubic ft.
Correspondence, manuscripts, census records, publications, clippings, photographs, notes, journals, scrapbooks.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Records of a social study undertaken by John Embree and his wife Ella Embree Wiswell of Suye-mura, a Japanese village, from 1935-1936.
BIOGRAPHICAL NOTE
John Embree received his BA from the University of Hawaii in 1931, his MA from the University of Toronto in 1934 and his PhD from the University of Chicago in 1937. He was Professor of Anthropology at the University of Hawaii, 1937-1941 and from 1943-1945, Associate Professor of Anthropology and head of the Japanese area studies of the Civil Affairs Training School for the Far East which the War Department set up at the University of Chicago for the training of military government officers for Japan and the Occupied Areas. From 1948-1950 he was Associate Professor of Sociology and Research Associate of Anthropology at Yale and in 1950 he was appointed Director of Southeast Asia Studies at Yale.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
Correspondence, newspaper clippings, census records, photographs, field notes and journals concerning the Japanese village Suye-mura, which John Embree and his wife Ella Embree Wiswell studied from 1935-36. In 1935 Embree received a grant from the Social Science Research Council to make a social study of a Japanese village. Includes a copy of John Embree's The Chinese Screen and lecture notes on the Civil Affairs Training School for the Far East.
SUBJECTS
Names:
Embree, John F., 1908-1950.; Wiswell, Ella Lury.; Social Science Research Council (U.S.); University of Chicago. Civil Affairs Training School.
Subjects:
Suye-mura (Japan).; Anthropology--Study and teaching.
Places:
Japan--Social life and customs.; Japan--History.; Japan--Study and teaching.
Form and Genre Terms:
Photographs.
INFORMATION FOR USERS
SERIES LIST
Series I. Suye-mura
Boxes 1-5
Series II. Publications Concerning Suye-mura, by Embree and Others
Box 6
Series III. Writings of John F. and Ella Embree
Box 2 Folders 26-32
Boxes 3-5
Series IV. Ephemera
Box 5
Series V. Photographs
Volumes 1-8
CONTAINER LIST
- Series I. Suye-mura
  - Census-ASO, 1935-1936 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Census-Hamanoue, 1935-1936 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Census-Hirayama, 1935-1936 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Census-Imamura, 1935-1936 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Census-Kakui, 1935-1936 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Census-Kawaze, 1935-1936 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Census-Nakashima, 1935-1936 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Census-Oade, 1935-1936 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Census-Tontokoro, 1935-1936 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Census-Yunoharu, 1935-1936 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Census-miscellaneous, 1935-1936 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Maps, 1935-1936 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Diary of a Japanese innkeeper's daughter (Box 1, Folder 13-16)
  - Scrapbook - ephemera, 1935-1936 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Unrevised manuscript- vols. I and II (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Clippings, publications, correspondence, 1953-2001 (Box 1, Folder 19-21)
  - Video correspondence, 1991-1996 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Photographic archive-list of photographs taken by John Embree and Ella Lury (Embree) Wiswell - guide created in 1985-86, 1935-1936 (Box 2, Folder 1-2)
  - Photographic archive list created in 1998, 1935-1936 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Photographs and correspondence-miscellaneous (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence-miscellaneous (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Miscellaneous material-clippings (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Reprints and inquiries-miscellaneous, 1954-1984 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Wiswell correspondence, 2000-2001 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Wiswell correspondence, 1995-1999 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Wiswell correspondence, 1990-1994 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Wiswell correspondence, 1988-1989 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Wiswell correspondence, 1987 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Wiswell correspondence, 1986 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Wiswell correspondence, 1985 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Wiswell correspondence, 1984 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Wiswell correspondence, 1983 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Wiswell correspondence, 1982 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Wiswell correspondence, 1981 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Wiswell correspondence, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Nishino correspondence, 1991-1994 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Ushijima correspondence, 1971-1989 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - The Women of Suye Mura - University of Chicago Press - correspondence, 1976-1982 (Box 2, Folder 22-23)
  - The Women of Suye Mura - reviews, 1983-1986 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Japanese translation of The Women of Suye Mura - clippings, correspondence, 1982-1988 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Draft manuscript of The Women of Suye Mura (Box 5)
  - Album of enlarged black and white photographs of Suye Mura (Box 5)
  - Catalog of the 1,720 prints, identifying each by date and place (Box 5)
- Series II. Publications Concerning Suye Mura, by Embree and Others
  - By John Fee Embree:
    - Suye Mura: A Japanese Village. Chicago: University of Chicago Press, 1939. (Box 6)
    - "Acculturation among the Japanese of Kona, Hawaii: Memoirs of the American Anthropological Association," Number 59. 1941. (Box 6)
    - "The Japanese." Washington, D.C.: Smithsonian Institution War Background Studies, Number 7. 1943. (Box 6)
    - (Compiled and annotated) Japanese Peasant Songs. Philadelphia: American Folklore Society. 1944. (Box 6)
    - The Japanese Nation: A Social Survey. New York: Rinehard & Co. 1945. (Box 6)
    - Suye Mura: A Japanese Village. Chicago: University of Chicago Press. (With a foreward by Richard K. Beardsley.) 7th impression. 1964. (Box 6)
    - Suye mura: Nihon no mura (Suye Mura: A Japanese Village) Translated by Uemura Notokaku. Tokyo: Nihon keizai hyoran sha. 1978 (Box 6)
  - By Arthur F. Raper:
    - The Japanese Village in Transition. Tokyo: General Headquarters, Supreme Commandeer for the Allied Powers, Natural Resources Section, Report #136. 1950. (A survey of 13 villages, one of which is Suye) (Box 6)
  - By I. Roger Yoshino:
    - "Selected Social Changes in a Japanese Village," 1935-1953. University of Southern California, Ph.D. dissertation. 1954. (Box 6)
  - By Morimitsu Ushijima:
    - "Suye Mura in Transition." Atlanta University, Master's thesis. 1959. (Box 6)
    - "Henbo sura suye mura (Suye mura in Transition)." Kyoto: Minerva Shobo. 1971. (Box 6)
    - Kumamoto: Zusetsu Nihon minzoku shi (Kumamoto prefecture: Illustrated Japanese Folklore). Kumamoto: Iwaski bijitsu sha. 1987 (Box 6)
    - Suye Mura, 1935-1985 (Photomonograph). Tokyo: Nihon keizai hyoron sha. 1988. (Box 6)
  - By Barbara Kawakami:
    - "The Position of Women in Rural Japan: Tradition and Transition in Suye Mura." University of Hawaii, Master's thesis. 1983 (Box 6)
  - By Chikara Yamano, Toshitaka Aiko, et al:
    - Ima katari tsutaeru: Suye no kurashi (Speaking of Life in Suye). Privately printed, ND. (Box 6)
  - By Tadayoshi Tsunematsu:
    - Kumamoto-ken Suye monogatari: furuki-o-tazunete (Kumamoto Prefecture, Suye's Story: Looking Back). Privately printed, 1991 (Box 6)
  - By Yoshi Nishi
    - (Editor and publisher): Tsuiso (Memoir). Privately printed, 1985. (Box 6)
    - (Editor): Kumamoto-ken, Kuma-gun, Suye-mura yakuba somuka (General Affairs Section of the Village Office of Suye Mura, Kuma County, Kumamoto Prefecture (Box 6)
    - Suye-mura hyakunen-no ayumi (A Hundred Year History of Suye Mura), 1989. (Box 6)
    - Suye-mura seko 100 shunen kinen: 1989 sonsei yoran (Commemorating the 100th Anniversary of the Establishment of Suye-mura: Report on the Village), 1989. (Box 6)
- Series III. Writings of John F. and Ella Embree
  - John Embree's Karuizawa journal, 1932 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - John Embree's The Chinese Screen (one of two copies), 1932 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Personal notes/correspondence (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - John Embree lecture notes - Civil Affairs Training School for the Far East (War Department), 1943-45 (Box 2, Folder 29-32)
  - Field Notes and Manuscripts - John Embree, 1935-1936 (Box 3)
  - Some of Ella Embree's notes, 1951
  - Ella and John Embree's journals - copies (Box 4)
- Series IV. Ephemera
  - Cloth and pipe tobacco case, gifts presented for John and Ella Embree upon leaving Suye Mura, 1936 (Box 5)
- Series V. Photographs
  8 large albums of 1,720 black and white photographs of Suye Mura taken by John and Ella Embree
  - Photographs 1-216, 1935-1936 (Volume 1)
  - Photographs 217-432, 1935-1936 (Volume 2)
  - Photographs 433-643, 1935-1936 (Volume 3)
  - Photographs 649-864, 1935-1936 (Volume 4)
  - Photographs 865-1080, 1935-1936 (Volume 5)
  - Photographs 1081-1296, 1935-1936 (Volume 6)
  - Photographs 1297-1500, 1935-1936 (Volume 7)
  - Photographs 1500-1720, 1935-1936 (Volume 8)